Hello everyone and welcome
to EnglishPod, my name is Marco.
My name is Catherine
and you've probably
heard us talking a little bit about
Small Talk the past few weeks.
We have another episode
about Small Talk and
we're going to teach
you some things that
you can say to people when you haven't
seen them or maybe even met them before.
That's right, today we're
going to talk to a stranger.
So we're going to
talk very briefly about
some casual topic and so let's jump
into the dialogue and see what happens.
Excuse me, is this seat taken?
No, please feel free.
Thanks a lot.
Do you work in Shanghai?
Yes, I do.
How about you?
No, I'm a tourist.
This place is amazing.
It's much bigger than I
imagined in much more exciting.
There's so much to see here.
You can say that again.
It's much more modern than people imagine.
Where are you from?
Well, let's see.
I'm from Kansas originally.
A much quieter and more
peaceful place than here.
That's for sure.
But I'm living in Paris right now.
Oh, Paris.
Wonderful.
I'd love to visit sometime.
All right, we're back.
So now we're going to take a look
at a lot of phrases on this occasion.
So let's go for Fluency Builder Part 1.
Fluency Builder.
All right.
So the first phrase we have is a very common
phrase if you're in a train or on a bus
or you hear the phrase, is this seat taken?
Right.
So Michelle came up to the stranger
and said, excuse me, is this seat taken?
That means is anybody sitting here?
It basically means, can I sit here?
Right.
But this is a very polite way of
asking if you can sit down in the seat.
You can also say it on a restaurant,
on a movie theater, in a classroom.
So remember this one.
This was a really, really common phrase.
So it's a very polite way
of saying, can I sit down?
That's right.
You're asking for permission, basically.
Is this seat taken?
Because what if a person
says, well, no, it's not.
Do you have to say, may I
sit down, may I take a seat?
Well, if they say, I'm sorry,
someone is sitting here.
That means that maybe
they're waiting for a friend.
And then no, you can't sit there.
OK.
But they say, sure, like
in the dialogue, feel free.
Then you're really basically
able to sit down a problem.
Right.
So the stranger answers by
saying, no, please feel free.
So he says, no, the seat is not taken.
Please feel free.
What does he mean by this?
OK, feel free is a
very unusual phrase in
English, but one that
you're going to hear a lot.
It basically means do what you want to do.
OK.
So if I want to sit down,
I say, is this seat taken?
If you say, feel free, Marco,
that means feel free to sit down.
OK.
So we can complete the sentence by
saying, no, please feel free to sit down.
But it's kind of stating the obvious.
You're saying, basically,
feel free to do what you want.
That's right, but you
could use it in other ways.
For example, hey, Marco, are
you using this pen right here?
No, no, feel free.
That means feel free to use my pen.
OK, very good.
And so then they started talking
about what they do, where they work.
And Michelle said, yes, I work in Shanghai.
How about you?
Oh, how about you?
Now, this is a really
important construction.
This is a really important
phrase in English.
And I think a lot of people
make mistakes with this.
So how about you means,
do you work in Shanghai?
I just said, I work in
Shanghai, but how about you?
Do you?
Right.
Exactly.
So that's saying, and
you, do you work here?
Or, and you, what do you do?
How about you?
Now, the common mistake with how about
you or using the construction, how about,
is that for some reason, some people
seem to think that it means how is it?
So for example, if someone
says, how about your weekend?
That's wrong.
No, we don't say that,
how was your weekend?
But in this case, how about you
always follows a statement, OK?
So yes, I do live in Shanghai.
How about you?
Right.
Do you live in Shanghai?
For say, I would like to eat a
hamburger and french fries.
How about you?
What would you like to eat?
Exactly.
So remember, that's the way
that you use how about, never
say how about your weekend
or how about your vacation.
And when you want to ask, how was it?
Don't say that.
No, basically, this is a
way to reply to someone
when they're telling you
about their experience.
You want to talk about yours.
That's right, OK?
So let's take a break.
Let's review everything.
And we'll be back with
Fluency Builder Part 2.
Excuse me, is this seat taken?
No, please, feel free.
Thanks a lot.
Do you work in Shanghai?
Yes, I do.
How about you?
No, I'm a tourist.
This place is amazing.
It's much bigger than I
imagined in much more exciting.
There's so much to see here.
You can say that again.
It's much more modern than people imagine.
Where are you from?
Well, let's see.
I'm from Kansas originally.
I'm much quieter and more
peaceful place than here.
That's for sure.
Uh-huh.
But I'm living in Paris right now.
Oh, Paris.
Wonderful.
I'd love to visit sometime.
All right, we're back,
so now let's continue
with some more phrases
on Fluency Builder.
OK, this first phrase is
one that I really like to use.
The phrase is from Michelle.
She says, you can say that again.
But she's talking about how
Shanghai is so big and so exciting.
And Michelle says, you can say that again.
Now, what does this mean, Marco?
That's right.
So she is basically
agreeing with the person.
The stranger says Shanghai is amazing.
It's great to-- there's so much to see.
Michelle says, you can say that again.
It's saying, I agree with you.
You are so right.
I really agree.
All right, so this is very emphatic.
That means that it's
more than just I agree.
It's-- I really, really agree.
The person really feels
something about this.
Feels passionately about it.
That's right.
So if you go to the movies and you say,
oh, that movie was terrible, you can say.
You can say that again.
Exactly.
That means, oh, I agree.
It was really bad.
That's right.
Now, when Michelle asks the stranger
where he was from, he says,
I'm from Kansas originally.
OK.
What's-- there is no way.
I'm original now.
I'm from Kansas originally
means maybe I don't
live in Kansas now, but
that's where I come from.
Origin originally.
That means, you know, at the beginning.
Right.
So just remember, Kansas, by the way,
is one of the states in the United States.
And so he's saying he's from Kansas.
But now he lives in Paris.
So that's why you say,
I'm originally from Kansas.
But I live in Paris.
All right.
So Marco, you live here in Shanghai.
But where do you come from originally?
Originally, I'm from Ecuador.
All right.
And I'm originally from Chicago,
but I currently live in China.
That's right.
OK.
So as he was talking about Kansas,
he also said that, well, it's obviously
a lot quieter and more
peaceful, and then he
ends his statement by
saying, that's for sure.
That's for sure.
And this is a phrase that we used
to add emphasis on something.
It's almost like saying, this is a really
quiet, much quieter and peaceful place.
That's for sure.
It really is.
It's not like you're adding
anything to the statement,
like no meaning, but you're
actually kind of making it more strong.
Right.
You're saying it's a fact.
It's a fact.
It's really this way.
So obviously, compared to Kansas,
compared to Shanghai is a lot more quieter.
That's for sure.
Or I could say that in Chicago in the
winter, it's a lot colder than Shanghai.
That's for sure.
Right.
So again, you're emphasizing
on your statement,
telling everyone that it's
very, very much like this.
This is how it really is.
OK.
So that's all the phrases we have for you
when we listen to our
dialogue one last time.
Excuse me, is this seat taken?
No, please.
Feel free.
Thanks a lot.
Do you work in Shanghai?
Yes, I do.
How about you?
No, I'm a tourist.
This place is amazing.
It's much bigger than I
imagined in much more exciting.
There's so much to see here.
You can say that again.
It's much more modern than people imagine.
Where are you from?
Well, let's see.
I'm from Kansas originally.
A much quieter and more
peaceful place than here.
That's for sure.
Uh-huh.
But I'm living in Paris right now.
Oh, Paris.
Wonderful.
I'd love to visit sometime.
All right, so small talk with a stranger.
This is actually a very common scenario.
If in a bus, in a train,
you sit next to a stranger.
This is more or less what
you're going to talk about.
Where are you from?
What do you do?
Where do you live?
That's right.
And you don't even have to talk about this
with a total stranger you could actually
use this with someone that you're working
with or, you know, just an acquaintance.
So basically, these are key questions
that you would ask someone
that you don't really know very well.
That's right.
And as you can see, you're not really
going into any deep personal questions.
It's very light, conversation,
very brief as well.
That's right.
And I would like to add that in
American culture, people often
think it's very rude to ask
someone, how much do you earn?
How much is your apartment?
How much is your car?
So, you know, in small
talk in American culture.
And I think a lot of Western cultures,
we don't talk about money or religion.
Yes.
So what religion are you?
So I think it's important to talk
about things that are very, very simple.
You know, what do you do for a living?
Where do you live?
How's the weather at these things?
Yes.
This is exactly, I think,
one of the main points
that when you're learning
a language such as English,
not only to understand the
language, but also the culture,
it's very, very different,
especially for example in Asian
cultures where it's no big
deal if you go to the hairdresser
and the hairdresser asks
you how much you earn.
But in the United States
or many Western countries,
it's not something that you talk
about, your salary, or that you really ask.
It's kind of personal information.
It is.
And if you talk about it, you might
make people very uncomfortable.
And so I recommend talking
about some of the things
that we've discussed here
and some of the things
that we've discussed in other
lessons in this series about small talk.
That's right.
And if you have any questions or
any comments about this lesson,
you can come and visit
us at englishpot.com.
We hope to see you guys there.
Until next time, bye.
Bye.
(upbeat music)